Good morning. Today's דף daf is ס"ה, Samech Hey, 65. We are
a little bit ahead and we're going to see if we can
get a full דף daf ahead because תשעה באב Tisha B'Av is
coming up. So we pick up at the bottom of ס"ה עמוד
א' Samech Hei Amud Aleph and the discussion here is the statement
of רב, Rav, which is going to last us throughout today with
a few digressions, about when you assess the payment for כפל Kefel
versus the payment for four and five, double and four and five,
versus the payment for the קרן, Keren, the principal. So a כפל
Kefel and four and five is a court-imposed financial punishment. It is
not a debt. It is not like a natural sort of incurring
liability. The court has to impose it. If you admit to it,
you're exempt from it. And therefore רב Rav says that those payments
are based on the value if you stole January 1 and it
was worth one, and the court case was December 1 and it
was worth four, or the reverse, then he says you pay for
the four and five based on when the court imposes the debt,
whereas you pay for the principal when you did the stealing because
that's when you incurred the fundamental liability.
And now the גמרא Gemara had some different, you know, ways of
limiting רב's Rav statement. It said that what do you call it,
that if he made it fatter or he made it thinner, then
that wouldn't change it because then he wouldn't have to pay for
what he added or he wouldn't have to benefit from the fact
that he made it worse. We're basically talking about a change in
market value. Even a change of market value if it went up
and he slaughtered it here because one of the examples is like
to sell it or slaughter it or he sold it, which is
another way of stealing, so then he would pay the principal also
based on the higher value because that's incurring another debt of the
principal. But if it just was around here, he didn't slaughter it,
then that's when he would pay this, you know, he'd do the
split, this based on when he stole and that based on the
higher amount, or if it was reversed, if it was four and
one, then it would always be this, the principal based on when
he stole and the two and the four and five based on
when he stood in the court case. Okay, so that was the
principle of רב Rav and now we're going to continue to try
to prove and develop this. So let's take a look. The גמרא
Gemara says like this.
תני רבי חנינא, tani Rabbi Chanina, three lines from the bottom. תני
רבי חנינא tani Rabbi Chanina לסיועיה לדרב, lesiyu'ei l'darav, רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina taught the following ברייתא beraita to bring support to רב. Rav.
בעל הבית ba'al habayit שטען טענת גנב בפקדון, sheta'an ta'anat gannav bipikadon,
see now you know why we spent the first two דפים dappim
of this פרק perek talking about טענת גנב. ta'anat gannav. So you're
already prepared for this case. So somebody who had been given an
object to watch and claimed that it was stolen or that it
was burgled ונשבע v'nishba and then he swore, so we know now
he's going to have to pay כפל, Kefel, והודה v'hodeh
but then he admitted. So in general, forget that he said גנב,
gannav, anybody that falsely swears as a way of keeping property, you
know, keeping something that was entrusted to him to himself and then
he admits it, brings a special קרבן korban called an אשם גזילות,
Asham Gezelot, a sin offering for stealing through the use of an
oath, and he pays back the owner plus a חומש, chomesh, a
fifth. So this guy did both because and because bringing the קרבן
korban and paying the חומש chomesh only comes through the act of
admission. Only when you admit it do you bring the קרבן korban
and pay a חומש. chomesh. כפל Kefel you normally pay only when
witnesses find you out. Okay, so this guy first of all because
it was a טענת גנב ta'anat gannav with a שבועה, shvu'ah, right
if you'd sworn falsely about an אבידה aveidah then the only thing
then there would never be a כפל, Kefel, but if you admitted
it you'd pay a חומש chomesh and bring a קרבן, korban, right?
So now because it was a גניבה, geneivah, it's possible we're talking
about both liabilities. But only if for the כפל Kefel you need
עדים, edim, for the קרבן korban and the חומש chomesh you need
to admit it. So you did all of that. Okay, so let's
take a look. אם
עד שלא באו עדים הודה, im ad shelo ba'u edim hodeh,
if you admitted before the witnesses came, so this ברייתא beraita basically
assumes that if you admitted prior to the witnesses then you're going
to remain then you'll be out of כפל Kefel even after the
witnesses come. Okay, so משלם קרן וחומש ואשם, meshalem keren v'chomesh v'asham,
then forget the כפל. Kefel. You got it? So you did this
oath about גניבה, geneivah, you would be liable כפל, Kefel, but you
admitted, and because it's a קנס knas your admission won't make you
pay, and that admission even gets you out of it according to
this ברייתא beraita even after the witnesses come. So if you admitted
first, כפל Kefel is off the table, and because you admitted then
you're going to bring your קרבן korban plus a חומש. chomesh. Fine.
That's case number one. But ואם משיבואו עדים הודה, v'im misheiavo'u edim
hodeh, if after the witnesses came you admitted it, so it's now
too late to get out of כפל. Kefel. Now you have both
liabilities. You have the liability of כפל Kefel because the witnesses came.
You have the liability of the קרבן korban and your חומש chomesh
because of your admission.
But your admission means nothing.
Yeah, so that's interesting. It's interesting but because your admission is from
the perspective of, you know, like doing a תשובה teshuvah or whatever,
you're right, you could have said that admission after the witnesses came
means nothing, right? But because it's like part of the whole point
about כפרה kapparah and תשובה, teshuvah, you know, they say like all
these people that are in the prison, you know, they could be
there 30 years, they could be going to, you know, be the
death penalty and they won't admit that they've done it. Right, it's
always, you know, that they've been framed. So even after the witnesses
came, that there's a power, it's interesting, there is a power of
the admission.
This is what you actually didn't know when the witnesses came?
Like it was No, no, no, you knew the witnesses came. You
could still deny it, fine, you know, you've got witnesses, I'm going
to pay, but I'm telling you I never did it, right? So
the act of the, you're right, that's interesting that the admission is
meaningful. Okay, so you have both liabilities here, it's כפל kafel plus
the קרבן korban and the fifth. Okay, ואם משבאו עדים הודה, ve'im
sheba'u edim hodeh, משלם תשלומי כפל ואשם בחומש, meshaleim tashlumei keful ve'asham
bechomesh, משלם תשלומי כפל, meshaleim tashlumei keful,
you pay double because you were a טוען טענת גנב, to'ein ta'anat
ganav, you pay double, okay, and the אשם, asham, you bring the
אשם, asham, you admitted. Now how about the fifth that you add
on? וחומשו, vechomsho, the extra fifth which is part of the כפרה
kapara and the admission, עולה לו בכפלו, oleh lo bekiflo, דברי רבי
יעקב. divrei Rabbi Yaakov. Rabbi Yaakov says, well, that's, you know, your
כפל kafel includes the extra fifth.
So you don't pay the fifth essentially?
Right, but we'll see in a minute how the גמרא Gemara deals
with that. Okay, so but he says you're in theory you're חייב,
chayav, but it's your כפל kafel includes it. וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim,
and the sages say, בראשו וחמישיתו. berosho vechamishito.
No, no, no, fundamentally there's no obligation for the fifth. You know,
so it says on the top of it you pay a fifth.
ממונא דמשלם בראש, mamona demeshaleim berosh, if they're only paying the principal,
that's what they understand משלם בראש meshaleim berosh means, then מוסיף חומש,
mosif chomesh, you add a fifth to the principal. ממונא דקמשלם בראש,
mamona deka'meshaleim berosh, this money you're paying כפל kafel for, and by
the way remember the כפל kafel obligation came first, so you can't
even conceptualize it as no, no, no, fundamentally I'm paying the קרן
keren plus, no, no, no, fundamentally it starts with כפל. kafel. And
then if something starts with not a קרן keren payment but a
כפל kafel payment, אין מוסיף חומש, ein mosif chomesh, you don't add
a fifth. So in principle they all agree you don't pay a
fifth, but one is conceptually it's included in the כפל kafel and
one is fundamentally you don't pay a fifth. רבי שמעון בן יוחי
אומר, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai omer, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai says not
only that, you don't even bring the קרבן. korban. אין חומש ואשם
משתלם במקום שיש כפל. ein chomesh ve'asham mishtaleim bemakom she'yesh keful. No,
no, no, like he agrees with בראשו וחמישיתו, berosho vechamishito, but he
says more than just you only when there's a principal is there
a fifth, only when there's a principal is there a קרבן. korban.
In a case where it starts as a כפל kafel case, there's
not going to be a fifth and a קרבן. korban. So according
to, by the way, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, Michael, right, effectively your
admission does nothing. Right now, you could, what you were saying, and
that would have been my intuition, maybe the admission it doesn't count
as an admission, he's not framing it that way. Right, let's say,
for example, here's another case. It wasn't גניבה, geneiva, it was גזילה.
gezeila. You took a שבועה shvua and it what you said it
was נגזל nigzal and you were lying, okay, and then witnesses came
and then you admitted, then you would do a חומש chomesh and
a קרבן. korban. So it's not because it doesn't count as an
admission. But he says once you're not paying the principal, you're paying
כפל, kafel, you're not going to bring a קרבן korban either. So
first we're going to look at this debate, I mean, let's take
a look. Okay, so how is this relevant for us? קתני מיהת,
katani mihat, we taught nonetheless, חומשו עולה לו, chomsho oleh lo,
that the חומש chomesh counts towards, you know, with, you know,
it counts, the כפל, kafel, that בכפלו, bekiflo,
I'm sorry, that for, you know, the חומש chomesh is part of
the כפל, kafel, דברי רבי יעקב. divrei Rabbi Yaakov. Now the גמרא
Gemara assumes that for the חומש chomesh to count with paying the
כפל, kafel, it has to be that it's distinct as a חומש.
chomesh. It can't be that it's hidden and, you know, if they're,
you know, in the כפל. kafel. It has to be like a
distinctly identifiable חומש. chomesh. So let's take a look. היכי דמי, heichi
dami, what's the case? אילימא דמעיקרא שויא ארבע ולבסוף שויא ארבע, ilima
de'me'ikara shavya arba u'levasof shavya arba, when you stole it was worth
four and when there was the court case it was worth
four, so חומשו עולה לו בכפלו, chomsho oleh lo bekiflo, what do
you mean that the חומש chomesh counts because you're paying the כפל?
kafel? כפלא ארבע וחומשא זוזא. kifla arba vechumsha zuza. The כפל kafel
is four and the חומש, chomesh, what's a quarter, what's a fifth
of four? One, of course, because the way you do a fifth
is it's a fifth after you pay it. So if you add
one to four, you'll have a total of five, so it'll be
a fifth of the final total. So the חומש chomesh is really
a quarter of the principal. Okay,
so therefore the גמרא Gemara assumes that the your כפל kafel would
not count as your חומש chomesh payment if it was, if the
identity of the חומש chomesh was obscured. Okay, so in that case
you're paying four, you can't count that as a חומש chomesh payment.
So
now obviously this is not because we're not just talking about a
debt, right? If I owe you two hundred dollars, if I owe
you one hundred dollars and I say, here, here's two hundred dollars,
keep the change, you can't say, oh, you didn't pay me my
debt because it wasn't a clear one hundred dollars there, right? You
obviously wouldn't say that. But a חומש chomesh is an idea of
a type of a כפרה. kapara. There's some ritual nature to it.
And therefore you sort of understand, I mean, Tosafot has a different
read of the גמרא, Gemara, but I'm going with Rashi. You sort
of understand the idea that if it doesn't look like a חומש,
chomesh, it looks like כפל, kafel, we can't give it sort of
that ritual role of a חומש chomesh to achieve כפרה. kapara. Okay,
so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So then it wouldn't count.
Okay, אלא לאו, ela lav, you must say, דמעיקרא שויא
ארבע ולבסוף שויא זוזי. de'me'ikara shavya arba u'levasof shavya zuzei. It started
with four and it ended with one. Okay, דכפלא זוזא וחומשא זוזא,
dikifla zuza vechumsha zuza, in that case, right, if it was four
and one, this is why it's a proof to Rav. If it's
four and one and Rav is right that you split the קרן
keren and the כפל, kefel, so you'll pay four for the קרן,
keren, one for the כפל, kefel, so your כפל kefel is the
same amount as your חומש chomesh payment because your חומש chomesh is
a חומש chomesh based on the principal. Okay, so if we're going
to have a case where כפל kefel and חומש chomesh are the
same, it must be that you're paying that the value went down,
so the כפל kefel will only be one. Yes, everybody got that?
No? Yes? Hello?
But the כפל kefel would be two, right?
No, you pay a total of five, you pay four as the
קרן keren plus one for the כפל. kefel.
כפל kefel is double.
כפל kefel is the extra one. Okay, all right.
So wouldn't רב Rav hold the other way around, when it went
from one to four?
He also holds that, but that wouldn't work with this case. Okay.
דכפילא זוזא וחומשא זוזא. D'kfeila zuza v'chumsha zuza. אלמא קסבר שגנב כשעת
גניבה וחומשא כשעת עמידה בדין. Alma kasavar she'ganav k'sha'as gneiva v'chumsha k'sha'as
amida b'din. You see that that's a nice support for רב, Rav,
that the amount of כפל kefel can change if the value of
the object changes. So the כפל kefel could be one even when
the original value was four. Okay, so isn't that a nice proof?
So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, no, not necessarily. I'll have a way
of explaining רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, that ברייתא braita without it being
a support of רב. Rav. לעולם דמעיקרא שויא ארבעה והשתא נמי שויא
ארבעה. L'olam d'meikara shova arba v'hashta nami shova arba. It was four
and it started four and ended four. So how could it be
that the כפל kefel is only a quarter of the original price?
Or how could it be, let me rephrase it, that the כפל
kefel and the חומש chomesh are the same amount? So he says
like this:
ודקא קשיא כפילא ארבעה וחומשא זוזא, V'deka kashya kfeila arba v'chumsha zuza,
you were bothered in that case the כפל kefel would be four
and the חומש chomesh would only be one. So הכא במאי עסקינן,
Hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? כגון שנשבע וחזר ונשבע
ארבע פעמים. K'gon she'nishba v'chazar v'nishba arba pe'amim. So you told me,
you told me like, you know, where's that thing that you have
of mine? I said it was stolen. Make me swear. Okay, I
take an oath. Then you say, no, you know, I still don't
believe you. I want you to take another oath. Fine, I'll take
another oath. Fine, I'll take another oath. Fine, I'll take another oath.
So I took four oaths. Okay, in that case when I finally
get around to admitting it, I'm going to pay a חומש chomesh
for every single oath that I took. Okay, and in that case
my כפל kefel will be four and my collection of חומשים chomshum
will be four. Okay, so even though you could say, well, each
חומש chomesh isn't distinguished separately in that case either, but as a
collection of חומשים, chomshim, you know, that counts.
So you don't pay the חומש chomesh on like the קרן keren
and then the חומש chomesh from before?
Right, the חומש chomesh is always on the
קרן. keren. והודה, V'hoda, okay. וחזר ונשבע ארבע פעמים והודה. V'chazar v'nishba
arba pe'amim v'hoda. והתורה אמרה וחמישיתיו, V'haTorah amra v'chamishisav,
it's fifths, fifths in plural.
התורה ריבתה חמישיות הרבה בקרן אחת. HaTorah rivsa chamishiyos harbeh b'keren achas.
Fine, so it can't be a proof from that. We could have
a case where the multiple חומשים chomshim equal the כפל. kefel. Fine.
So that was an attempt to prove רב. Rav. Let's finish up.
We're going to now finish with this discussion here about this idea
of the overlapping of the חומש chomesh and the כפל kefel and
then we're going to get back to רב's Rav statement. אמר מר
וחכמים אומרים בראשו וחמישיתו. Amar mar v'chachamim omrim b'rosho v'chamishiso. ממון המשתלם
בראשו מוסיף חומש ממון שאינו משתלם בראשו אינו מוסיף חומש. Mamon hamishtalem
b'rosho mosif chomesh, mamon she'eino mishtalem b'rosho eino mosif chomesh.
So only when you pay the principal do you pay the חומש.
chomesh. If you're paying כפל, kefel, you don't pay חומש. chomesh. אבל
אשם מייתי, Aval asham maysei,
but clearly the difference between the חכמים chachamim who say fundamentally you
don't have an obligation of חומש chomesh and רבי שמעון בן יוחאי
Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai is whether you pay the אשם. asham. מאי
שנא? Mai shna? So the גמרא Gemara says what, how do they
distinguish that in the פסוק? pasuk? מאי שנא חומש דלא משלם? Mai
shna chomesh d'lo mishalem? Why do you not pay the חומש chomesh
when you're paying כפל? kefel? דכתיב בראשו, D'ksiv b'rosho, on its principal,
on the base, וחמישיתו, v'chamishiso, you add a fifth. אשם נמי לא
משלם, Asham nami lo mishalem, so you also shouldn't bring an אשם
asham when you're paying כפל. kefel. דכתיב בראשו וחמישיתו ואת אשמו. D'ksiv
b'rosho v'chamishiso v'es ashamo.
And then it says, and the אשם. asham. So presumably the אשם
asham is also based on only paying the principal, which is exactly
what רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai says. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר לך רבנן, Amar lach rabanan, רבנן rabanan would
tell you.
Where does it say ואת אשמו? v'es ashamo? That's the פסוק. pasuk.
וחמישיתו יוסף עליו ואת אשמו יביא להשם. V'chamishiso yosef alav v'es ashamo
yavi l'Hashem. No, בראשו וחמישיתו יוסף עליו לאשר הוא לו יתננו ביום
אשמתו. B'rosho v'chamishiso yosef alav la'asher hu lo yitnenu b'yom ashamaso. That's
the פסוק. pasuk. And the
next
פסוק pasuk is that.
All right, so it's the next פסוק. pasuk.
Hold on. בפרשת ויקרא. B'parshas Vayikra.
אמן בויקרא. Amen b'Vayikra. One minute.
Hold on. Oh,
נפש כי תחטא ושבעה לבטיה בתוספותיהם למלוג
ולשמנה ובכל אשר ישבע אדם בשקר ושלמה ממנו...
Nefesh ki secheta v'shiva l'vatea b'tosafoseihem l'malog
u'leshamna u'vchol asher yishava adam besheker v'shilmo mimenu... ואת
אשמו יביא להשם.
V'es ashamo
yavi l'Hashem.
One
minute. This פסוק pasuk
is from
ויקרא. Vayikra.
אמן בויקרא. Amen b'Vayikra.
One minute.
Oh no, that's a different one. Hold on. That's not אשם גזילות.
asham gezeilos. One minute. Yeah, או
מצא אבידה ויכחש בה ונשבע על שקר על אחת מכל אשר יעשה
האדם לחטוא בהן והיה כי יחטא ואשם
והשיב את הגזילה אשר גזל או את העושק אשר עשק או
את הפקדון אשר הופקד אתו או את האבידה אשר מצא או מכל
אשר ישבע
עליו לשקר ושלם אותו בראשו וחמישיתיו יוסף עליו לאשר הוא לו יתננו
ביום אשמתו ואת אשמו יביא להשם.
O matza aveida v'kichash ba v'nishba al sheker al achas m'chol asher
ya'aseh ha'adam lachato bahen v'haya ki yecheta v'ashem v'heshiv es hagezeila asher
gazal o es ha'oshek asher ashak o es hapikadon asher hupkad ito
o es ha'aveida asher matza o m'chol asher yishava
alav l'sheker v'shilem oso b'rosho v'chamishisav yosef alav la'asher hu lo yitnenu
b'yom ashamaso v'es ashamo yavi l'Hashem. Right. That's why it sounds like
it should be אשם שבועה. asham shvuah. All
right, so that's a good point. So you're right. I mean the
גמרא Gemara is going to say that, but you're right, the גמרא
Gemara is only going to focus on the word את. et. It
should have focused on all the words that come in between. So
I don't know what to say to you. It's a good point.
It's an excellent point. Okay. So אמרו ליה רבנן, amru leh Rabbanan,
the רבנן Rabbanan would tell you, את et פסקי לקרא. paskei likra.
So Michael is absolutely correct. It does not just say אשמו יביא
לה'. ashamo yavi l'Hashem. There's a lot of words before אשמו יביא
לה'. ashamo yavi l'Hashem. But there's a lot of words between when
it says בראשו וחמשיתו berosho vachamishito until it gets to the word
אשמו. ashmo. So the fifth is connected to paying the base amount.
So the אשם asham is not. רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai would tell
you, ואת ve'et ערבי. arvei. The ו' vav reconnects it. It says,
no, it's linked to the other payments and it's just like those
other things, it's only when you start with the base. Okay. ערבי
קרא. arvei kra. רבנן אמרי לך, Rabbanan amri lach, the other רבנן
Rabbanan will say to you, לא ליכתוב רחמנא lo lichteiv Rachmana לא
ו' ולא את. lo vav velo et. Don't write the ו' vav
and don't write the ואת ve'et and then, you know, if you
really wanted to link it. את et is doing a function of
actually holding them separate. רבי שמעון בר יוחאי אמר לך, Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai amar lach, את לא סגי דלא כתבי. et lo sagi
d'lo katvei. No, no, no, it had to write את et to
create a certain amount of a break between them. Why? לאפסוקי בין
ממון גבוה לממון הדיוט. le'afsukei bein mamon gavoah lemamon hedyot. It wouldn't
be appropriate to talk about the fifth and the קרבן korban in
one breath because the fifth is money paid to a person and
the קרבן korban is given to Hashem and we don't want to
treat them as the same type of a thing. Okay. So anyway,
everybody agrees that it's fundamentally, it needs to start with a base,
not with כפל, kefel, but the rabbis say the קרבן korban is
different. The קרבן korban is brought under all circumstances. And רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai says, no, even the קרבן korban
is linked to paying only the base, not paying כפל. kefel. Okay,
that's that. That's the whole thing of the fifth. Back to our
discussion, which is the different payments between the time of stealing and
the time of the court case. Let's take a look. אמר רבי
אילא, amar Rabbi Ila, says רבי אילא, Rabbi Ila, this will be
fun. גנב טלה ונעשה איל, ganav taleh vena'aseh ayil, if you stole
a sheep and it became a ram, okay, עגל ונעשה שור, egel
vena'aseh shor, or a calf and it became a cow or an
ox, so נשתנה בידו וקנאו. nishtanah beyado ukena'o.
So now this is a different object and you own it. Now
we are going to get into, while
we're in the process of wrapping up רב's Rav statement about the
difference between קרן keren and כפל kefel when you pay, we're now
going to start and be introducing ourselves in the whatever if we
get to tomorrow's stuff,
but particularly the דף daf coming up, all the different ways in
which a גנב ganav is קונה koneh or a גזלן gazlan is
קונה koneh an object. And those ways are, let me just put
them on the table for you right at the beginning. The most
basic way that the גמרא Gemara accepts is something called שינוי. shinnui.
But שינוי shinnui means a classic שינוי shinnui is שינוי מעשה. shinnui
ma'aseh. I do something and I change it. I steal a piece
of wood and I build it into a box. Okay, I've made
it something completely different. Therefore, it now stops being the owner's, it's
mine. I have to reimburse the owner for the cost, but the
object now belongs to me. This is an idea that when a
different type when when a גנב ganav when the things changes, I
don't have to return the object anymore to the owner, I just
have to pay them for it. By the way, there are two
ways about looking about it. One way is that it's a type
of a קניין. kinyan. The same way when I take the object,
I take it as if I bought it, I'm taking it into
possession, I do משיכה, meshichah, I do הגבהה, hagbahah, I do something
of that nature. But still, the other guy didn't want to give
it to me, so I don't really own it. But in some
הלכות halachot we actually speak about having some partial ownership and קנייני
גניבה kinyanei gneivah and so on. Well, you could say if I
intensify that and take more possession of it and do an act
that makes it more mine and makes it less his, like I
completely physically change it, then I forcefully have taken possession of it.
It's sort of like, you know, the גמרא Gemara has a discussion
about like when property seized in war, right? Is that גניבה, gneivah,
is that גזילה, gezeilah, or is it like at certain point if
you forcefully seize something and totally make it yours, it stops being
the other person's? I guess we could politicize that conversation really quickly,
but we're moving on. Okay. So anyway, so that's one way of
understanding קנייני גניבה. kinyanei gneivah. Another way is just like, no, it's
not like I did an act of taking possession. But the תורה
Torah says I return והשיב את הגזילה veheshiv et hagezeilah especially by
גזילה gezeilah אשר גזל, asher gazal, that you stole, כעין שגזל. ke'ein
shegazal. If it's in the same way in which it was stolen.
If it's seen as a different object, then it's I, you know,
then it just somehow automatically stops being yours. I have no obligation
to return it. Once I stop having an obligation to return it,
right, I just somehow naturally take possession of it. So another person
couldn't, but like I can. So it's still based on the idea
that it starts with the fact that I have some ownership of
it when I take it, but what's preventing that full ownership from
expressing itself is my obligation to return it. Once that obligation goes
off, I'm able to keep it for myself. So those are the
two conceptual models.
One is an act of taking possession. The other is you don't
have to return what you don't say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha
lefanecha. Is that what you're saying?
You well הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha is usually you're entitled
to say it even if it's worth nothing. You don't have a
חיוב chiyuv to return it when it's not כעין שגזל ke'ein shegazal
and therefore becomes yours, but you still have to pay the money.
הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha gets you off of paying the
money. Okay. So those are the two conceptual models. One is an
act of taking possession. The other is... is when the מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah* of returning it goes away, I naturally now own the object.
Now, here are the different types of ways of קנינים *kinyanim*. Okay,
there is the most classic is שינוי מעשה shinoy ma'aseh. *shinuy ma'aseh*.
That has the best of both for גניבה gneivah וגזילה *gneivah ugezeilah*.
Right, שינוי מעשה shinuy ma'aseh *shinuy ma'aseh* that has the best of
both worlds of the two models I just explained. You physically change
the object. You build the wood into a box. So number one
because I'm actually physically doing it, I am taking possession of it.
That act of taking possession. Because it's a new thing, right, it's
a different thing. I don't have a need to return it, okay.
That's has both of them. It has the act and it has
that it's new. Okay, now, here are here are two variations of
that, okay. One is called שינוי השם shinui hashem, *shinuy hashem* which
can happen by itself. I didn't do anything. This calf became an
ox. I did nothing. It could be looked at as a new
object. Now you could claim I don't look at that as new,
if it's a natural type of a development that happens by itself,
I just look at it as a grown-up calf. I don't look
at it as new. We could debate that, but let's assume we
agree we do look at it as new. It is a new
name. But I didn't do it through any particular act, right? So
this whatever, okay. So this is something that's just has the new,
but does not have the act. Now you have another case of
יאוש yeush, *yeiush*, יאוש yeush *yeiush*. The owners give up hope. I'm
never going to see it again. Now if you give up hope
about the lost object and I pick it up, it's mine, right?
Because your giving up hope makes it more detached from you. You
gave up hope of getting back this גניבה gneivah *gneivah*, I kept
on holding onto it, I've taken possession. So that's in a way
an act of, I mean it's not like I changed it, but
the act of taking of holding onto it after you've given up
hope, even though it's still the same object, right, that's more an
act of a קנין kinyan. *kinyan*. Okay, so it's just so it's
pretty cool, right?
But isn't יאוש yeush *yeiush* passive?
No. The owners' יאוש yeush *yeiush* plus your okay, plus being in
your רשות *reshut*, your, you know, holding of it, okay. It's not
a transformative act, but it's an act like a normal act of
a קנין kinyan. *kinyan*. The owners give up and it's in my
property and it's a taking of possession. All right, this is not
a taking of possession, this is just the thing changes.
So if he's a piece of יאוש yeush *yeiush* in the middle
of the street and I'm not doing anything, then it's not mine?
Possibly not, although whether your קנינים *kinyanim* are enough, the natural קנין
Kinyan *kinyan* you have in it, but that's an interesting question. Okay,
and then we can also talk about יאוש ושינוי רשות yeush v'shinuy
rishut. *yeiush v'shinuy reshut*. So it might also be a case here
of יאוש yeush *yeiush* plus שינוי shinui, רשות *shinuy reshut*, a third
party gets it, okay, and then that's the third party is taking
possession of it. Okay, so this is all about taking possession, this
is about changing, and this that's the best of the two. So
those are the basic models of how a גנב gannav *ganav* takes
possession of an object. Let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. אמר רבי לא *Amar Rabbi La*.
Okay, גנב gannav, טלה ונעשה איל taleh v'na'aseh ayil, *Ganav taleh v'na'aseh
ayil*, if he stole a sheep and it became a ram, עגל
ונעשה שור shor *Eigel v'na'aseh shor*, a calf and it became an
ox. נעשה שינוי shinui. בידו וקנאו *Na'aseh shinuy beyado ukenao*. So it
became a שינוי shinui *shinuy* in your hands like automatically and you
take possession of it. So that's not a שינוי shinui מעשה *shinuy
ma'aseh*, that's what we're going to get called in a little bit
a שינוי השם shinui hashem *shinuy hashem*. So once it's now a
new object, טבח ומכר *Tavach umachar*, if you slaughtered or sold it,
שלא טבח שלא מכר *Shelo tavach shelo machar*, you're slaughtering something that's
yours or you're selling something that's yours. So you don't pay four
or five. I did?
Oh, no. Okay. Okay, then you don't pay four or five. איתי
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina. לרבי לא *Eitei Rabbi Chanina l'Rabbi La*, so
Rabbi Chanina challenged Rabbi La. גנב Ganav טלה ונעשה איל ayil, *Ganav
taleh v'na'aseh ayil*, we have a ברייתא Braisa *Baraita*. גנב Ganav טלה
ונעשה איל *Ganav taleh v'na'aseh ayil*, עגל ונעשה שור *Eigel v'na'aseh shor*,
exactly your case. משלם תשלומי כפל kefel ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה כשעת הגניבה
*Meshalem tashlumei kefel utashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah kesha'at hagneivah*. You pay כפל kefel
*kefel* and four and five like when you stole. So first of
all that goes against רב Rav *Rav*, because it says you pay
כפל kefel *kefel* and four and five when you stole, not בהעמדה
בדין *beha'amadah badin*. But it also goes against רבי לא *Rabbi La*,
because it's saying that you're going to be paying four or five.
Okay, ואי סלקא דעתך קניה בשינוי *V'i salka daitach kanya b'shinuy*, according
to you that you took possession when it changed, אמאי משלם *amai
meshalem*, why are you paying? שלא טבח שלא מכר *Shelo tavach shelo
machar*, you're just slaughtering and selling something that's already yours. That's exactly
your case. And it says you pay four and five. אמר ליה
Amar lei, *Amar lei*, so he said back to him, אלא מה
*ela mah*? So what do you think? How would you read that
ברייתא Braisa *Baraita*? שינוי shinui. לא קני lo kani. *Shinuy lo kani*?
You'd say that change doesn't make you take possession because it's all
like automatic, so you don't take possession of it. If that's true,
אמאי משלם כשעת הגנבה *amai meshalem kesha'at hagnava*? How do you explain
how that ברייתא Braisa *Baraita* works according to רב Rav, *Rav*? Why
are you paying according to the time you stole? משלם כהשתא *Meshalem
kehashtah*, pay four and five based on now, right? So this ברייתא
Braisa *Baraita* is a real challenge. A, it seems to indicate that
you don't own it when it makes this natural change, which goes
against רבי לא *Rabbi La*. B, it goes against רב Rav. *Rav*,
it says you pay it based on now, not based on the
original. אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar lei*, he said back to him,
כהשתא היינו טעמא דלא משלם *kehashtah hainu ta'ama d'lo meshalem*. No, for
me it works. I don't think that you own it as a
result of this, but here's why you don't pay the amount of
its value right now, why it doesn't work with רב Rav *Rav*.
Because היינו טעמא דלא משלם משום דאמר ליה דגנב *hainu ta'ama d'lo
meshalem mishum d'amar lei deganav*. He's got this exactly right. תורא גנבי
מינך? ממינך? miminakh? Did I steal an ox from you? דכרא גנבי
מינך? Dikra ganvi minakh? Did I steal a ram from you? No,
I stole a little calf, I stole a little sheep. So therefore
what? Because therefore, and we're going to remember we touched on this
yesterday, the same way yesterday we said that if you fattened it,
you're not going to pay the higher value because of what you
added to it, this גמרא's Gemara. taking it one step further. Even
if you didn't actively fatten it, if it's some type of a
different object, כפל kefel is כפל of what you stole. So therefore,
if something changed price, but it's the same object, you could say,
how do you figure out how to do the—how much is that
object worth? Do I look at the price then or the price
now? But it's still two or four or five times the object
that was stolen. But you stole a calf, you didn't steal a
cow. So why are you going to pay four five times the
value of a cow? It's ultimately still the value of what you
stole. Which—which price you attach to it is a different question. So
he says, look, when it's a different object, it's not different enough
because it happened all by itself for you to own it. But
it is different enough that we're not going to pay four, five
or כפל based on this. This isn't the same object. It's going
to be based on the original one. Okay, so that's what he
says back. That's a pretty reasonable argument. אמר
ליה, so he said back to him, רחמנא ליצלן מהאי דעתא. Rachmana
litzlan me'hai da'ata. God should save us from such opinions. So אמר
ליה, so he said back to him, אדרבה רחמנא ליצלן מדעתא דידך,
Addaraba Rachmana litzlan mida'ata didach, the opposite, God should save us from
opinions like yours.
So you gotta love it. What? Okay, yeah, so you got—so it's
quite funny like you normally don't have this type of an exchange,
especially because it's just same to you, oh yeah! So anyway,
but, you know, but where were you when they were giving out
brains? No, anyway. So—but the funny thing is like it's not exactly
clear like why they're feeling the opinion is so objectionable, but presumably
you understand. What he's saying is if you're willing to consider it
so different that you don't pay four or five because it's a
different object, then you should be conceding to me that you're not
going to pay—that you're going to own the object, right? Once you're
conceding that it's a different object, you should concede that you own
it. And he says no, God forbid, that's a crazy logic. It's
a different object, but you didn't take possession of it. It happened
by itself. So just because it's different doesn't mean you own it,
but it does mean you're not going to pay double or four-five
based on it. Okay, so now we've introduced ourselves into the world
of שינוי, shinui? and we've also had this new reservation on רב's
Rav idea that you're not going to pay כפל or four and
five if the object changes, only if it's the same object. Let's
continue in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, now we're going to really turn
to this issue of שינוי. Shinuy So מתקיף לה רבי זירא, Matkif
lah Rabbi Zeira, so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira challenged this whole thing
about this שור and the איל, about how could you say that
you don't own it. So he says, וניקנינהו בשינוי השם? Venikninhu beshinui
hashem? Okay,
so now he's saying look, I get you're saying it happened naturally,
and so on, it's not a different object, but doesn't it—isn't it
called something different? Isn't that his point? And isn't the fact that
it has a different name enough to take possession of it?
So again, you could have argued that you need to do an
act, it doesn't happen automatically, and maybe—but אמר רבא, Amar Rava, but
רבא Rava says it's not even really a new—called something new. שור
בן יומו קרוי שור, Shor ben yomo karui shor, איל בן יומו
קרוי איל. Ayil ben yomo karui ayil. An ox even one day
old is called an ox, a ram even one day old is
called a baby ram. Okay, how do you know? שור בן יומו
קרוי שור, Shor ben yomo karui shor, דכתיב, de'chtiv, שור או כשב
או עז כי יולד. Shor o chesev o ez ki yivaled. An
ox, a sheep or a goat that is born, so it's already
called an ox when it's born. ואיל בן יומו קרוי איל, Ve'ayil
ben yomo karui ayil, and a ram one day, דכתיב, de'chtiv, ואילי
צאנך לא אכלתי. Ve'eilei tzonecha lo achalti. יעקב Yaakov says to לבן,
Lavan, I did not eat the rams of your sheep. איליי הוא
דלא אכל, כבשים אכל? Eilei hu delo achal, kevashim achal? What, the
rams you didn't eat, but the little baby sheep you ate? אלא
לאו שמע מינה איל בן יומו קרוי איל, Ella lav shema mina
ayil ben yomo karui ayil, it means any of the sheep. Okay,
so that's an interesting point. In order to say that something is
a new name, what defines a new name? And if you can
certainly understand here that he's not just saying, I mean he's partly
saying maybe, you know, what's the norm amongst how people talk, you
know, the societal norms and conventions around what you call and label
things. But it could also be the fact that as we said,
this is a natural way in which something grows and develops. So
therefore how much—I mean, you know, you would think like a moth
and a butterfly probably would be a שינוי השם, shinui hashem? you
know, that's so radically different. But if this ultimately is just something
growing up, right, so he's saying that's not something that we would
call a different object. Okay, so here's—so what he's saying is in
principle, we don't argue that a שינוי השם shinnui hashem, would קונה,
koneh, but this case is not something to be called a different
object. All right, now the גמרא Gemara continues. מכל מקום קשיא. Mikol
makom kashya. Now we've still got a problem. So we got one
question which is, is this a שינוי Shinuy השם? It happened naturally.
Are you קונה koneh it? Now, there's one opinion that says no,
and the reason that you don't pay for—and you pay four and
five based on the original value is it's different enough that you
pay four and five based on the original, not based on now,
but it's not a different name and you're not going to own
it. But according to רבי אלעא Rabi Ila who says you are
קונה koneh it, what does he do with the ברייתא Braisa. that
says you pay four and five? According to him, you'll never pay
four and five because you were קונה, koneh, you've got a ברייתא
Braisa against רבי אלעא. Rabi Ila. So the גמרא Gemara says מכל
מקום קשיא, mikkol makom kashya, you've got this contradiction to רבי אלעא.
Rabi Ila. אמר רב ששת Amar Rav Sheshes הא מני בית שמאי
היא, ha mani Beis Shammai hi, no no no, the ברייתא Baraisa
that says that you pay four and five is a position of
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. דאמרי De-amri because בית שמאי Beis Shammai say
שינוי במקומו עומדת ולא קני. shinui bimkomo omedes velo kani. A שינוי
Shinuy stays in its place. We don't look at a changed object
as a different object and there's no קנין. So basically, רבי אלעא
Rabi Ila holds the idea that when the object changes, you own
it, it's a different object. Okay, but the ברייתא Baraisa that says
even after it became a ram and an ox, whatever, you still
are going to pay four and five, that holds that a שינוי
Shinuy, you do not take possession of something by virtue of a
שינוי. Shinuy Now, where does בית שמאי Beis Shammai say that you
don't take possession of something by virtue of a שינוי? Shinuy, Let's
take a look. דתניא De-tanya we turn to the ברייתא. Baraisa נתן
לה באתננה, Nasan lah be-esnanah, somebody gave to a prostitute in her
fee because you're not allowed to bring let's say a lamb given
to a prostitute for her fee as a קרבן. korban. So let's
say rather than what he gave to this prostitute it was חטין,
chittin, wheat, ועשה סלת, ve-asah solet, and she ground it into flour.
Or זיתים, zeisim, olives, ועשה שמן, ve-asah shemen, she made it into
oil. Or ענבים, anavim, grapes, ועשה יין, ve-asah yayin, or grapes that
she made into wine. So is this the same object that was
given to her? You see in a lot of הלכות halakhos we
want to ask this question, when something changes is it seen as
the same object, right? So תני חדא אסור, tani chada assur, one
ברייתא Baraisa teaches she can't use it for her אתנן esnan for
her קרבן, korban, ותני חדא מותר, ve-tani chada mutar, and one says
it can be used. So it's that's the debate, do we look
at this as a different object? ואמר רב יוסף Ve-amar Rav Yosef
תני גיורא דמבי אספורק, tani Giyora de-mei Asporak, this person teaches that
בית שמאי אוסרין ובית הלל מתירין. Beis Shammai ossrin u-Beis Hillel mattirin.
This debate is between בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל, Beis
Hillel, that בית שמאי Beis Shammai say it's still the same object.
Now, מאי טעמא דבית שמאי? mai ta'ama de-Beis Shammai? What's the reason
of בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? דכתיב גם De-ksiv gam לרבות שינוייהם. le-rabbos
shinuiyyehem. It
says לא תביא אתנן זונה ומחיר כלב בית ה' אלהיך לכל נדר
כי תועבת ה' אלהיך גם שניהם. lo savi esnan zonah u-mechir kelev
beis Hashem Elokecha lekhol neder ki so-avas Hashem Elokecha gam sheneihem. They
are both an abomination to God. So why did you have to
use the word both? So he says גם לרבות שינוייהם, gam le-rabbos
shinuiyyehem, even after they changed, they still remain forbidden.
Okay, בית הלל Beis Hillel הם. hem. No, what is it? What's
the פסוק? pasuk? כי תועבת ה' אלהיך
הם גם שניהם. ki so-avas Hashem Elokecha hem gam sheneihem. I guess
it would be הם, hem, the הם hem of שניהם, sheneihem, they,
they are an abomination, ולא שינוייהם, velo shinuiyyehem, not the new version
that they take. If they change, it's a different thing and it's
not a problem. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai הוא הם ולא ולדותיהם.
hu hem velo veladoseihem. No no no, when it says them, it
means that if you give a sheep to this prostitute and the
sheep gives birth, then the baby sheep or whatever, the lamb is
okay. Okay, so that's the only the object itself, but בית שמאי
Beis Shammai would say but whatever form the object takes. And בית
הלל Beis Hillel says no, not only the object itself, only the
object in its original form, הוא דאסר. hu de-assar. ובית הלל, U-Beis
Hillel, בית הלל Beis Hillel say תרתי שמע מינה, tarti shema mina,
both are true. הם ולא שינוייהם, Hem velo shinuiyyehem, only the object
itself and not in its some new form that it's taken. הם
ולא ולדותיהם, Hem velo veladoseihem, and only the object itself and not
a something that it gives birth to. So בית הלל Beis Hillel
says if it changes it's a different object, and בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says even if it changes it's still forbidden. ובית הלל, U-Beis
Hillel, הא כתיב גם? ha ksiv gam? What do they do with
the word גם? gam? גם Gam seems to be expanding the category.
So it says גם לבית הלל קשיא. gam le-Beis Hillel kashya. Fine,
that word גם gam is a problem for בית הלל. Beis Hillel.
Okay, now
here is a very important question: How do we jump from a
debate around whether you can bring something as an אתנן זונה, esnan
zonah, you know, this special הלכה halakha about bringing as a קרבן,
korban, to this question of whether a גנב Ganav, takes possession? So
first of all, you have to do it's a two-step thing. First
of all, you could say this debate is only in the world
of אתנן, esnan, it's no bigger, broader conceptual issue, right? בית הלל
Beis Hillel may generally hold one way, but by אתנן esnan the
פסוק pasuk tells them this. בית שמאי Beis Shammai normally hold this,
but by אתנן esnan פסוק pasuk tells them. So maybe it's a
very specific הלכה halakha about אתנן esnan and completely irrelevant. Even assuming
that it betrays a larger principle, what would that larger principle be?
The larger principle is not about whether you take possession of something.
This is not a question about קנין. So what the larger principle
is, and תוספות Tosafos makes this point is: The larger principle is
in order to say that once something changes I take possession of
it if I'm a גנב, Ganav that means that I have to
conceive that I look at something as having changed, right? Right? Meaning,
it's nice to say that there's a principle of if it changes
you take possession, but we first have to concede that we're willing
to look at it as a new object, and you know, sometimes
we're not like a שור ונעשה איל shor ve-nasah ayil other cases
we won't look at it as a new object. So what the
גמרא Gemara is saying is בית שמאי's Beis Shammai position is: I
never look at anything as a new object. Okay now I don't
know where how far it would go, you know, I mean literally
like if you would... pulverize something and reconstitute it in a laboratory,
I don't know exactly, okay? But בית שמאי Beis Shammai says some
type of a natural within a certain range, at least, I refuse
to look at it as a new object. It's just the old
object in a different form. So I can't talk about a גנב
ganav taking possession. I can't even begin the conversation. I refuse to
recognize it as a new object, right? It's like you painted it,
it's like you whatever, it's the same thing. Whereas בית הלל Beis
Hillel says from אתנן Esnan you see that בית הלל Beis Hillel
concedes, first point is, it's a new object. Once it's a new
object, remember number one is, it's you can use it as a
קרבן Korban by an אתנן. Esnan. Because it's a new object, I
can also talk about a גנב ganav. taking possession of it, okay?
So we've got the idea of שינוי shinnui here. So what we
have is בית שמאי Beis Shammai says it's the same object, okay,
and therefore it's forbidden for an אתנן, Esnan, and בית הלל Beis
Hillel says it's a different object, okay? Because it's a different object,
now we have some possibilities. For an אתנן, Esnan, it's okay because
it's not what was given, and for a גנב, ganav. these are
not the same הלכות, Halachos, okay, but they all are based on
recognizing it as a different object. And for גנב ganav, it's a
different object, then you can take, then you can do a קנין
on it, you know, for the reasons we laid out before. So
that's but בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, he basically eliminates the whole conversation.
So the ברייתא Baraisa that says that if it's a שור ונעשה
איל, Shor v'na'aseh ayil, טלה ונעשה איל, you pay four and five,
that's בית שמאי Beis Shammai who refuses to recognize things as being
different. But רבי אילא Rabbi Ila who said you take possession of
it and you don't have to pay four and five, he's going
like בית הלל Beis Hillel that recognizes that things change, yes.
Can you just say that בית שמאי Beis Shammai he just says
those three and doesn't say why?
I understand, all of this is the גמרא Gemara reading it into
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, yes.
Exactly, exactly, and it could have been a special אתנן Esnan הלכה,
Halacha, it didn't have to be a כל התורה כולה kol hatorah
kullah הלכה, Halacha, absolutely. But this is גמרא Gemara reading it in,
which then makes it, you know, interesting for us conceptually whether or
not it's originally what בית שמאי Beis Shammai meant. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says
עד כאן לא פליגי ad kan lo pligi back to top of
ס"ו עמוד ד'. Samech Vav Amud Daled. Until now we're only debating
אלא דמר סבר שינוי קונה ומר סבר אין שינוי קונה. ella d'mar
savar shinuy koneh u'mar savar ein shinuy koneh. Okay, the debate here
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai is whether שינוי
shinnui works to take possession or really it's one stage earlier, whether
שינוי shinnui, as the גמרא Gemara said a minute ago was במקומו
עומד, bi'mkomo omed, whether the thing is still considered, the language before
was more precise, whether even after it changes it still is where
it always was, it still is considered to be the same object.
אבל לעניין שלומי aval l'inyan shillumei כולי עלמא מודו. kulei alma modu.
I'm sorry, I think the מר mar here was not, oh I'm
sorry, the מר mar here was not בית הלל Beis Hillel בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. The מר mar here was רבי אילא Rabbi Ila
and רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina רבי אילא Rabbi Ila and רבי חנינא
are only debating by the case of the of the calf becoming
a an ox about whether it's considered to be the same object
or a different object, meaning even if everybody in principle agrees that
we concede to שינוי, shinnui we could debate whether the idea of
a little baby calf growing up constitutes a שינוי shinoy or not.
Okay, so there the debate was whether or not you actually are
going to see it as a new object and pay and whether
you're still be liable if you slaughter it, okay. אלא דמר סבר
שינוי קונה ומר סבר אין שינוי קונה, ella d'mar savar shinuy koneh
u'mar savar ein shinuy koneh, אבל לעניין שלומי, aval l'inyan shillumei, but
regarding how that ברייתא Baraisa says the payment is made, right? If
you're not going to be קונה koneh it because it's like בית
שמאי Beis Shammai or because you don't consider it to be a
שינוי, shinoy
what that ברייתא Braita, says is in a context in which you're
not קונה koneh it, it says כולי עלמא כדמי עיקרא משלם. kulei
alma kide'mei ikara meshallem. That ברייתא Braita says you pay the four
and five based on the value when it was a calf if
in a case when you're not קונה koneh it. So why is
that? That goes against רב, Rav's okay? דתניא, de'tanya, here's the ברייתא
says משלם תשלומי כפל ותשלומי ארבעה וחמשה כעין שגנב, meshallem tashlumei kefel
v'tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah k'ein she'ganav, like when it was stolen, like when
it was a calf. So לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב, leima tehei tiyuvta
de'Rav, let's say this is a contradiction on רב. דאמר רב קרן
כעין שגנב ותשלומי כפל ותשלומי ארבעה וחמשה כשעת עמדה בדין, de'amar Rav
keren k'ein she'ganav v'tashlumei kefel v'tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah k'shat amada badin, right?
So that's we essentially dealt with that a minute ago, but the
גמרא Gemara is now re-asking it. That ברייתא says you pay based
on the value of the calf, not on the value of the
cow. Why is that? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא, amar
Rava, so he's the answer is going to be in four words,
and there's a big debate what these four words mean: שית כדמי
עיקרא דמים כשל עכשיו. sheit kide'mei ikara damim k'shel achshav.
Excuse me, five words. שית sheit is like the original price, דמים
damim is like the current price. Okay, that explains that. Moving on.
Okay, so what does that mean? So תוספות Tosafos says, I'll first
tell תוספות Tosafos because תוספות Tosafos is more easy based on what
we said before. תוספות Tosafos says that's another way of saying what
the גמרא Gemara said earlier which was, what did I steal a,
did I steal a ram from you, did I steal a cow
from you, which is if the animal change, if the object changes
in value, when רב says you try, you have different sayings about
when it was stolen and when עמדה בדין amada badin etc., that's
when it was the same object, it just changed in value. Then
we can say you got to pay back, you know, you stole
a sheep, it's still a sheep, you got to pay back four
sheep. Okay, how much is a sheep worth? So do we look
at current market prices or do we look at market prices from
a year ago? But conceptually you're still paying. Four sheep, four lambs,
that's what you stole. But if it started as a lamb and
it ended as a ram, so we can't say you got to
pay four rams. You didn't steal four rams. You pay four lambs.
So we're going to look at the lamb. Now we might look
at the lamb at today's market prices. That would actually be a
way in which you would both do כמעיקרא k'me'ikara and כדהשתא. k'dehashta.
Okay, when you stole it lamb was worth a dollar. Now it's
a ram worth a thousand dollars and lambs are worth four dollars.
So could be we make you pay four lambs times four dollars,
right? When you look at the question of how much the dollar
market value you assign to it, that's when רב says you look
at today's market values. But if you look at what object are
you multiplying by two or four or five, you're multiplying the object
that was stolen, not some new object that's here right now, right?
That makes a lot of sense, okay? And that's basically what the
גמרא Gemara. had said before this as well. Just to sort of
give you a variation of that, it might be based on the
same principle. רש"י Rashi says it's not a question about whether the
animal changed, it's a question of what units you're paying in. If
you come and say, I want to pay back, I stole lambs,
I want to pay back in lambs, okay? So then I'm going
to pay back based on the original price. But if I want
to pay back cash, I'm going to pay back at today's market
price. Okay, so it's a little bit harder to, I mean, it
seems like it's based on a similar type of an idea of
a conceptual, do we conceptualize it like you stole money or do
we conceptualize it like you stole an object? Anyway, I don't want
to get into that. I just want to mention it. תוספות's Tosafos's
explanation is certainly the simplest based on what we've seen and it
makes an enormous amount of sense. You pay four times the object
you stole. What is the value of the object you stole? Then
we might want to look at today's market prices rather than those.
But the four times or the five times or the two times
is times the object you stole, not times some new object right
now. Okay, now we are going to put the rest to this
whole רב's idea of קרן כעין שגנב keren k'ein sheganav and we
are going to look at what is most people have the most
fun with, which is this question about שינוי shinoy. or about types
and ways in which you קונה גניבה. koneh gneivah. Okay, so we've
already discussed שינוי shinoy השם, we've discussed something that changes naturally without
an action, about whether that in certain circumstances does it really get
a new name or not? And we've discussed a debate of בית
הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai whether you acknowledge even when
something even changed through an action, whether you're willing to first start
and admit that it's conceived as a new object. If it's a
new object, then we can talk about taking possession, we can talk
about a lot of potential consequences. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara אמר רבה, Amar Rabbah,
says רבה, Rabbah, שינוי קונה כתיבא ותנינא. shinnui koneh ktiva v'tanina. The
idea that שינוי shinuy works for a גנב to take possession is
both written in the תורה Torah and taught in the Tannaitic material.
כתיבא, Ktiva, it says in the תורה, Torah, והשיב את הגזילה אשר
גזל, v'heshiv et hagezeilah asher gazal, you should return the object that
you stole. Now we've shifted to גזילה. gezeilah. We're assuming for now
that גניבה geneiva. and גזילה gezeilah are all the same. Okay, מאי
תלמוד לומר אשר גזל? mai talmud lomar asher gazal? Why does it
say the object that you stole? To tell you, אם כעין שגזל
יחזיר, im k'ein shegazal yachzir, if it's in the state it was
when you stole it, that's when you have an obligation to return
it. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, but if not, so you don't have
to return it. You get to keep it, it's yours, ודמים הוא
דמשלם, v'damim hu d'meshallem, you just have to pay the money but
you don't have to actually return the object. The object no longer
belongs to the owner once it has changed and it's not in
the way in which you stole it. Okay, so that's how I
get it from the פסוק. pasuk. תנינא, Tanina, and it's also taught
in a משנה, Mishnah, because the משנה Mishnah says later on, הגוזל
עצים ועשאן כלים, hagozel eitzim ve'asaan keilim, you stole wood and you
turned it into like boxes or some vessels, you know, a fork
and a spoon, whatever you did with them, צמר ועשאן בגדים, tzemer
ve'asaan bgadim, or you stole wool and you made it into garments,
משלם כשעת הגזילה, meshallem k'sha'at hagezeilah, you don't give back your nice
new garments and your nice wooden box. You pay the value that
thing was worth when you stole it. Okay, so that's one ברייתא,
the teaching that you do not, that you now own the thing
and you don't give back the nice brand new beautiful thing you
made from it, you just pay the value when you stole it.
אינמי, Einami, here's another משנה, Mishnah, and it's a ברייתא I meant
משנה, Mishnah, לא הספיק ליתנו לו עד שצבעו. lo hispik litno lo
ad shetzeva'o. Let's say you went ahead and this is not a
גניבה geneiva. case. So again, it's interesting when we cross boundaries and
we look at other areas of הלכה halacha and make analogies. But
you now have when you do the shearing of your sheep, you
have to give a gift of it to the כהן, kohen, ראשית
הגז, reishit hagez, the first of the shearings, once you shear a
certain amount. Let's say you sheared the requisite amount you're obligated to
give it to the כהן, kohen, but before you gave it to
the כהן, kohen, you dyed all the wool. Okay, so now it's
not the same wool and you don't have to give it to
him, which is quite interesting because you would think that that's not
a שינוי, right? I mean I think there's a much bigger שינוי
a calf becoming a cow than wool becoming dyed. I mean it's
you know, but I don't know, I mean maybe you don't just
dye it, maybe you know you clean it, you thread it, you
do all these things, it really. It does transform in the process.
Maybe it's not just color. You know, it's bigger, like you made
raw wool, raw shearings into like marketable dyed, you know, strings of
wool. I don't know exactly the degree of change. Anyway, לא הספיק
ליתנו עד שצבעו. Lo hispik litno ad shetzva'o. You didn't give it
to the כהן kohen until you had dyed it. פטור. pattur. You
don't have to give it. It's no longer considered the same wool.
אלמא שינוי קונה. alma shinoy koneh. You see, once it changes, you
take possession. Now, does it mean you take possession because you like
steal it from the כהן, kohen, or does it just mean that
in that case, it's not the same thing and therefore, if it's
not the same thing, you don't have an obligation to give it
to the כהן? kohen? I mean, it never was his yet. It
was yours that you had to give. Okay, so that's where he
says, but שינוי is obvious, especially if it's a שינוי מעשה. Notice
that at least, well, he wasn't explicit, but anyway, for now we'll
assume he means like a real שינוי that you did directly בידיים,
beyadayim, with your hands. So that's in the פסוקים, psukim, it's in
the משניות. mishnayos. No question to me about the effect of שינוי.
Right? We could debate like about a sheep becoming a ram, is
that really considered a new name or not? What happens when it
happens by itself and not something you did actively? We could debate
the parameters, but there's no question שינוי works. יאוש, yeush he says,
I got some more questions about. יאוש yeush, is when the owner
gives up hope of getting it back.
Okay. יאוש yeush, he says, אמרו רבנן דניקני. amru rabbanan d'nikni. I
know that the rabbinic tradition is that יאוש yeush works. מיהו לא
ידעינן, mihu lo yadinan, what I don't know is אי דאורייתא אי
דרבנן. ei deoraisa ei derabbanan. Does it work biblically or does it
only work rabbinically? Okay, this is when it's יאוש yeush in the
hands of the גנב. It's not that it's gone to a third
party. I stole it from you. You gave up hope of getting
it back. Now I own it. Okay. It didn't change. You just
gave up hope of getting it back. Now I own it. I
don't know if that's biblical or rabbinical.
Okay. מידי דהוה אמוצא אבידה, midi dehavay amotzei aveidah, like what happens
when you find a lost object. מוצא אבידה, motzei aveidah, now if
you find, if I find a lost object you lost after you've
given up hope of getting it back, I get to keep it.
So מוצא אבידה לאו כיון דמיאש מרי מיניה מקני דתיתי לידיה, motzei
aveidah lav kivan d'miyash marei minei mikni d'tesei l'yadei, since if, when
the owner gives up hope of getting it back before it gets
into the hands of the finder, קני ליה, kanei lei, the finder
is allowed to keep it. And the logic there is, let's just
stop for a moment and explain what the logic is. Why do
I keep your lost object after you've given up hope? Because
once it's lost, it's sort of out of your control. Your ownership
of it has been weakened, right? Your degree of using it, accessing
it, protecting it. So it's only, it's more like, you know, ownership
in name only at that stage, right? You don't have any practical
control over that. Once you actually give up hope of getting it
back, the only thing that at a certain stage made it yours
was you still seeing it as yours. That even though physically it
wasn't under your control, certainly in your psychically it was still yours.
Once even that has broken, you say, I forget it, I'm never
going to find it. There's nothing that's really left to attach it
to you. So it's free for somebody to come and take possession.
Your whole ownership has become so tenuous and weakened both physically and
mentally out of your possession. That's the idea of why יאוש yeush
allowed them to come and take it. Okay. Now, why is it
different after you have יאוש yeush after I find the object? Because
if I find the object and then you have יאוש, Yeush, as
soon as I found it, I had a מצוה to return it
to you. So my holding onto it was holding onto it for
your behalf. So at that stage, it was back under your possession,
as it were. So therefore, my יאוש, Yeush right, your יאוש Yeush
didn't sever the connection because at that stage I was holding it
for you. That's why it works by an אבידה. aveidah. Okay, let's
now see how that might translate by a גניבה. gneivah So let's
read that again. Okay. So
יאוש
אמרו רבנן דניקני מיהו לא ידעינן אי דאורייתא אי דרבנן. yeush amru
rabbanan d'nikni mihu lo yadinan ei deoraisa ei derabbanan. אי דאורייתא, ei
deoraisa, if it's
דאורייתא, deoraisa, מידי דהוה אמוצא אבידה, midi dehavay amotzei aveidah, like finding
a lost object. מוצא אבידה לאו כיון דמיאש מרי מיניה, motzei aveidah
lav kivan d'miyash marei minei, when you find the lost object, the
logic is that since the owner's give up hope, מקני דתיתי לידיה,
mikni d'tesei l'yadei, before it gets to the hand of the finder,
קני ליה, kanei lei, he takes possession.
אי נמי כיון דמיאש מרי קני ליה, ei nami kivan d'miyash marei
kanei lei, since the owner's given up hope, you should take possession.
אלמא קני. alma kanei. Therefore, you should take possession. Now there's an
obvious difference. How is it different, this case than the אבידה aveidah
case? Oh, if יאוש Yeush works by אבידה, aveidah, it should work
by גניבה. gneivah, Tell me what the difference is.
Well, אבידה aveidah you don't know whose it is. Here, you stole
it from a...
okay, but no, but if I find your אבידה aveidah after you've
given up hope, even if I know it's yours, I get to
keep it. Okay.
When by the does the יאוש Yeush. work by אבידה? aveidah? When
it occurs at what stage?
Before the guy finds it. When here, the יאוש Yeush occurs what
stage? After the guy had already stolen it. Right? So that's the
obvious difference. All right. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. או
דלמא לא דמי לאבידה, o dilma lo dami l'aveidah, or you'd say,
it's not like אבידה. aveidah. אבידה הוא דכי אתא לידיה בהיתרא אתא
לידיה. aveidah hu deki ata l'yadei beheiteira ata l'yadei. By אבידה, aveidah,
when it came into your hand, it came into your hand legally.
It came into your hands, it was already מותר. mutar. The guy
had already had the יאוש, Yeush; and it was allowed for you
to take it. Okay, אבל
האי, aval hai, this, כיוון דבאיסורא אתי לידיה, keivan d'be'issura asay l'yaday,
it came with your hands and you had violated. You didn't have—it
wasn't that the יאוש Yeush occurred first. First you stole it. So
in that case, the יאוש Yeush should not work. Okay, מדרבנן הוא.
m'derabbanan hoo. מדרבנן, m'derabbanan, maybe you only own it now not דאורייתא.
de-oraita. The יאוש Yeush doesn't work דאורייתא de-oraita now. This would be
like somebody found an אבידה aveidah and then there was יאוש. Yeush.
In that case, the יאוש Yeush, doesn't work. You stole it and
then there was יאוש; Yeush the יאוש yeush shouldn't work. So in
this case, מדרבנן הוא. m'derabbanan hoo. Only the Rabbis let you keep
it. דאמרו רבנן נקנה—the d'amroo rabbanan niknay Rabbis say you can keep
it מפני תקנת השבים m'pnei takanat hashavim for the sake of encouraging
people to return things. I mean, they're not going to return it,
but in order to encourage people to admit to things, right? If
we're going to say, you know what, you can keep the object,
you don't have to give it back, just pay the money. Alright?
So it's rabbinic, but biblically, actually no, because it occurred after you
took possession. רב יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef amar, and רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says יאוש אינו קונה ואפילו מדרבנן. yeush eino koneh v'afiloo m'derabbanan.
יאוש yeush by itself does not work even rabbinically, and that's according
to most ראשונים rishonim the way we פוסק. pasken. When will יאוש
Yeush, work? I stole it, you gave up hope, and then I
gave it to a third party. So from—that's called יאוש Yeush ושינוי
רשות. From the third party's perspective, he's getting it after the יאוש.
Yeush. But for me, since I took possession before the יאוש, Yeush,
the יאוש Yeush coming later will not work. Okay, so רב יוסף
Rav Yosef says יאוש כדי—is yeush k'di another way it's said in
the גמרא—יאוש alone without exchanging hands afterwards לא קני. That's רב יוסף'ס
Rav Yosef's position, whereas רבא'ס Rabbah's position here is—or רבא'ס Rabbah's position,
excuse me, is יאוש Yeush does work, maybe דאורייתא, de-oraita, maybe מדרבנן.
m'derabbanan. Now, let me take a minute. We won't go further right
now. Let me—we haven't caught up anymore, but let me take a
minute to say something about: what is the logic to think it
works דאורייתא? de-oraita? How do you answer this obvious difference? By an
אבידה, aveidah, it doesn't work after the guy finds it. So how
could it work by גניבה gneivah after the guy steals it? Right?
Isn't that an obvious difference? So let me tell you, תוספות Tosafot
asks this question, but I'm going to tell you what I think
is a really good answer to this, which I didn't see in
תוספות—maybe Tosafot somebody else says this—which is exactly the difference I just
said to you. By an אבידה, aveidah, when I find your object,
I am now holding on to it on your behalf. In that
case, okay, when you then have יאוש, Yeush, it's like you had
יאוש Yeush on something that was in your house. Let's
say you thought you lost your wallet on the street and it
turns out that actually, all along, it had been in your backyard.
Okay? And then I say, oh, I walked into your backyard and
I picked up your wallet after you had יאוש. Yeush Oh, it
was יאוש, Yeush so I can take it for that. No! It
never—it was in your—יאוש Yeush only works when it's out of your
control. If you weren't aware of it, but ultimately it was in
your possession, יאוש Yeush, obviously doesn't work. Well, when I find that
lost object and I am planning on returning it to you, it's
like it's in your backyard, right? That's why it doesn't work. But
think about—compare that to the case of the גנב. If I steal
the object, every single minute my holding of it is not holding
of it for you. It's the exact opposite! My holding of it
is an attempt to take it away from you. So in that
case, even though I first took possession of it before יאוש, Yeush
it is actively being pulled away from you and the יאוש Yeush
could still be effective. Alright? So even though it's true that when,
after somebody finds an אבידה, aveidah, the יאוש Yeush is in perspective,
after somebody takes a גניבה, the יאוש Yeush. could very well be
effective. Okay, so that would be the argument that יאוש Yeush, works,
you know, by itself. There's one other difference which I'll just say,
which תוספות Tosafot points out, which is that here you still have
to pay back the money. You know, by a גניבה—by an אבידה,
aveidah, when you're allowed to keep it, you're allowed to keep it
without giving back any money. So anyway, but that has—there's other ways
of dealing with that. But okay, but this is the גמרא'ס Gemara's
question. רבא Rabbah says שינוי of course works, שינוי מעשה at least.
יאוש, Yeush I know it works. Traditionally, I know we have a
tradition—you know, I know the Rabbis say it works. I don't know
if it's biblical or rabbinic. Laying out a very interesting question of:
is it like יאוש by אבידה aveidah or not?
The difference being that here the יאוש came after it came in
possession of the גנב'ס ganav's hands. Is that enough to say that
it does not work biblically? But minimally it works rabbinically. And רב
יוסף Rav Yosef says יאוש by itself does not work. If a
third party gets it, so that is like the אבידה—he, aveidah the
third party, got it after the יאוש. But if you, the גנב,
after יאוש, it's still the same object; you still have to return
it. Okay, so we'll see tomorrow the playing out of this debate
about whether יאוש works by itself or not.